[SPEAKER_00]: So, we have a question on five hindrances, and...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it starts with a quote from a sutta that... just, well, generic description of the hindrances from the sutta, saying, these five things are obstructions, hindrances, that encircle the mind, weaken the wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: What five?
[SPEAKER_00]: Essential desire is an obstruction,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a hindrance encircling the mind, weakener of the wisdom, ill-will, sloth and dopore, restlessness and remorse, and doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an obstruction, a weakener of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the five obstructions, hindrances, encirclers of the mind, weakeners of the wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the...
[SPEAKER_00]: So the question is and says...
[SPEAKER_00]: Previously, I was addicted to getting pleasure by following whatever felt good, which only led me to agitation and depression.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fortunately, I made the effort to investigate my situation, and by doing so, I gained perspective on it, seeing the danger in my choices that led to my addictions and subsequent depression.
[SPEAKER_00]: I then made effort in cultivating virtue and restraint, which led to contentment, but also to gaining an even higher perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm now able to see certain bad mental states that I'm addicted to, or simply cannot stop indulging in when they appear, specifically the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: I welcome lust, indulge anger, incline towards distraction, play with my restlessness and wrestle with confusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although I do not lose my previously cultivated level of perspective by becoming unrestrained and unvirtuous, I'm still struggling to attain a higher perspective due to my subtle involvement with these five obstructive mental states.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can I cleanse my mind of these things?
[SPEAKER_00]: What am I missing?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, so when the practice reaches the stage of you recognizing the five hindrances for what they are, but then at the same time not giving in to unvirtuous behavior and losing your restraint, that's pretty much the indicator where you should really be seeking some stricter forms of seclusion and isolation, because
[SPEAKER_00]: By increasing solitude, again, not as a rule of thumb.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean that whenever you increase solitude, you'll get to see the subtle states.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that can be done for the wrong reasons and prior development, as we often speak about, like there is an order of develop... the gradual training requires developing... the gradual developing in a certain order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, solitude, as a next step in your development, comes pretty much after, as the Buddha said, you have been established in virtue, established in sense restraint, established in the right view, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yes, as the question points out, they are obviously
[SPEAKER_00]: higher to not indulge with, because they're on the level of the mind, their mental state, deeply rooted mental pressures, you know, pressure of sensuality, pressure of ill-will, and, eh... if, eh... if that person is still living in the environment that is, at the same time,
[SPEAKER_00]: bombarded with other sort of sense objects and pulls and distractions and duties and requirements and so on, you simply won't have enough composure and enough strength to endure things on that mental level without, you know, either dismissing it or giving in to it and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, surmounting the four... in order to surmount the five hindrances, then the secluded lifestyle is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why, then, the jhāna would follow from there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And goes same in the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha says, basically, that
[SPEAKER_00]: Once, you know, having been established in sense-restraint, virtue, watchfulness, not giving in, not breaking the precepts, purifying your mind of the mental states, in other words, you know, not giving in to bad behaviors and bad cultivations, then you can go to solitude, and then that solitude will bear fruit towards the complete seclusion from these unwholesome states, even internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's then... the description carries on, the first jhāna, the second jhāna, and so on, in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if this is the factual state of affairs, as in if whoever asked this is clear about their level of progression and this is accurate, then, yeah, pretty much the only thing you specifically, the person who asked the question, needs to do is try and spend prolonged periods of time in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when
[SPEAKER_00]: When these deeply rooted, pressing mental states, hindrances, the encirclers of the mind, and weakness of the wisdom arise, well, there will be nothing else taking away, you know, your energy, your time, distracting you, and you will be able to then apply the same principle towards those mental states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Principle of not welcoming, not delighting, not running away, not distracting from, and certainly not acting out of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, in that seclusion, you can endure those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, the more you endure it, then, the... basically, the less fuel is being provided for those states to return at the... in the same intensity or at the same strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it will take time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, okay, now I go to seclusion and boom, hindrances disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to be living and dwelling in seclusion and prefer in seclusion in order to do the work that now you recognize needs doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Addressing the five hindrances on the level of the mental state.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, for somebody that might not take that long, but for other people it can take practically a long time, which
[SPEAKER_00]: Which doesn't, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how long it takes, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the worth...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the work worth doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the next step would be seclusion and then... that would result in that higher perspective or, like, let's say, higher levels of disowning of your own mental states correctly, without, you know, dismissing them or just kind of applying the theoretical view that, oh, this is not mine, this is anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: You basically need to have endured the mental hindrances long enough without acting out of them,
[SPEAKER_00]: And due their pressure, and due their pain, and due their discomfort, and due their dirt, burning, amber, all these descriptions that the Buddha gave, and then you will realize this is not worth holding.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not worth possessing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever they're pointing at to, for me, you know, to have or to deal with, it's not worth engaging.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how I free myself from the
[SPEAKER_00]: burning embers of sensuality or, you know, the pressure, the rabid kind of anger and whatever else kind of emotions might take over the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as for, you know, our more general audience that's equally sort of interested in overcoming hindrances, just to emphasize again, it's important to recognize that there is a certain order of development
[SPEAKER_00]: And although, yes, it would be great if you could just, you know, enter jhāna here and now, and then deal with everything else, that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not how the gradual training works, and that's not what the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by all means, strive to uproot the hindrances, but you need to recognize that in order to even start seeing the hindrances correctly, as we said in a number of previous talks,
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to recognize that, first and foremost, your behavior, your sense restraint, your watchfulness need to have been thoroughly, thoroughly developed in face of that, you know, pain and pressure of centrality and nil-will and external circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, depending on what's
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, what stage of the gradual training a person might be, the practice is then either to develop virtue, unshakable virtue, seeing the danger in the slightest fault, recognizing the intentions behind your actions as the root of the, you know, what defines wholesome is wholesome, unwholesome is unwholesome, taking responsibility for it, which then results in watchfulness, and then
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressures of the hindrances, which are exhibited in that broadest mental sense, is going to become more and more discernible, more and more obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can actually address it on that level, without needing to act out of it, without needing to resist it, try to outrun it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a person, through self-honesty, discovers that their virtue still hasn't been, you know, thoroughly developed, they still break it, sense restraint, they still give in, then, again, yeah, be honest about it and recognize that, although you have a burning desire and a strong determination, inspiration to deal with the hindrances, you won't be dealing with them until these prerequisites are addressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, yeah, if you address the prerequisites,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will kind of be dealing with the hindrances, even if you don't necessarily want to, specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, even in this original question, the fact that this person recognizes the pressures on the level of these bad mental states that, you know, that are affecting him on that level,
[SPEAKER_00]: But he's still not breaking the virtue or losing the restraint, means, okay, no, that's already a beginning of correctly addressing the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the fact that they were able to ask a question, how do I cleanse my mind of, specifically, the hindrances on this level, you know, without breaking virtue, without losing sense restraint, means like, okay, so, the phenomenon of that, the width of the hindrances, the domain of the hindrances, is becoming clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you really wanna
[SPEAKER_00]: Feel that domain, that pressure, properly, to the full extent, and learn how not to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the seclusion comes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will amplify it, it will clarify it, it will unclutter it, and it will be felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it's like a full extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, it's not going to be pleasant, but how unpleasant, as I often say, how unpleasant it will be, depends on, you know, how addicted to sensuality and acting out of your will you were before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: One way or the other, you will have to go through some withdrawals and not acting out of that pressure on the level of the of the mental hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yes, if, like, you know, if sometimes that pressure gets... just gets too much, or if the solitude gets interrupted, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That work is not automatically undone, for as long as you don't break the virtue and become unrestrained, for as long as you don't go too far the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if something, you know, demands you to sort of come out of your solitude and deal with and so on, you will be able to address it and then go back to it and pick up where you left, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, you know, the hindrance of doubt might make you doubt that and make you wanna break the precepts and everything else for the sake of dealing with hindrances again.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, person who has been able to recognize the hindrances on the level of the mental states for what they are, will see this as a doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just trying to trick you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as long as the virtue remains intact, seeing the danger in the slightest fault, being mindful of your intentions, even if you come and go out of solitude, the work that you did before in that solitude is not automatically lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you go back, you pick up pretty much the level you left it at.